Register of the Robert H. Adleman papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert H. Adleman papers
1939-1970
72075
Hoover Institution Archives
17 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope, 28 sound tape reels (10.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, questionnaires, transcripts of interviews, drafts of writings, galleys, research notes, sound tape reels, photographs, and maps relating primarily to the First Special Service Force (composed of American and Canadian troops) and its operations in Italy and Southern France during World War II. Used as research material for the books by R. H. Adleman, The Devil's Brigade, Rome Fell Today, and The Champagne Campaign.
Adleman, Robert H., 1919-1995.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of some sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to other sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1972.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1919 May 7 Born, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
1937-1939 Student, Rutgers University
1941-1945 U.S. Army Air Forces Received Air Medal and Presidential Unit Citation
1948 LL. B., Temple University
1966 Author, The Devil's Brigade
1968 Author, Rome Fell Today
1969 Author, The Champagne Campaign
1970 Author, The Bloody Benders
1995 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, questionnaires, transcripts of interviews, drafts of writings, galleys, research notes, sound tape reels, photographs, and maps relating primarily to the First Special Service Force (composed of American and Canadian troops) and its operations in Italy and Southern France during World War II. Used as research material for the books by R. H. Adleman, The Devil's Brigade, Rome Fell Today, and The Champagne Campaign.
Allied Forces. Special Service Force, 1st.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--France.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Italy.; Anzio, Battle of, Anzio, Italy, 1944; Audiotapes.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1945-1970 (Box 1)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1966-1970 (Boxes 1-6)
  - "The Devil's Brigade"
    - Research notes, drafts, etc. (Box 1)
    - Research notes, drafts, etc. (Box 2)
  - "The Champagne Campaign"
    - Research notes, drafts, etc.
    - Research notes, drafts, etc. (Box 3)
  - "Rome Fell Today"
    - Galleys
    - Galleys (Box 4)
    - Research notes, drafts, etc.
    - Research notes, drafts, etc. (Box 5)
    - Research notes, drafts, etc. (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous drafts
- SUBJECT FILE, 1940-1970 (Boxes 6-16)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, reports, interviews, questionnaires, and research notes, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - The AAF in the invasion of Southern France (Box 6)
  - Airborne Operations
  - Alpes - Maritimes
  - Anderson, Colonel Kingsley (diaries)
  - Anderson, Colonel Kingsley (diaries) (Box 7)
  - Anzio to Rome (Battle, 1944)
  - Bibliography (computer card file)
  - "A Bolt from the Blue, 1941-1945"
  - Cannes (France)
  - "Champagne Campaign"
  - Command Missions
  - Criminality
  - 88th Infantry Division (Box 8)
  - 85th Division
  - 5th Army - Unit reports
  - 1st Airborne Task Force, Headquarters
  - 1st Regiment - Interviews
  - First Special Service Force
    - Memoranda
    - Reports
    - Records
    - Press releases
    - Publications (Box 9)
    - Radio broadcasts
  - First Special Service Forcemen
    - Miscellaneous
    - Recollections
    - Reunions
  - 550th Battalion
  - 509th Parachute Infantry Battalion
    - General
    - Interviews
    - Questionnaires
  - 517th Regiment (Box 10)
  - "Five Years, Five Countries, Five Campaigns with the 141st Infantry Regiment"
  - 45th Division
  - 442nd Infantry Regiment
  - 460th Parachute FA
  - IV Corps
  - Frederick, General Robert T.
  - "The French Drive on Rome"
  - "From the Riviera to the Vosges in 30 Days"
  - German propaganda dropped at Anzio
  - Headquarters - Interviews
  - Index
  - Intelligence Operations (Box 11)
  - Interviews
    - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Legault, Conrad
  - Maps
  - Military service for prisoners and former prisoners
  - Monaco
  - Nice (France)
  - "Operation of Fate" (Hollis)
  - Ovenden, A. W. (diary)
  - Page, Getty (Director, American Red Cross)
  - "Plough Project"
  - Pyke, Geoffrey
  - Regional Liaison Detachment "B" - Civil Affairs (Nice, France)
  - Report for "Operation Dragoon,", 1944 August 22
  - Report of Operations - II Corps in Italy (Box 13)
  - Rome - Capture of
  - "Rome Journal"
  - Second Regiment
    - Interviews
    - Interviews (Box 14)
  - Selective Service System
  - Service (Maintenance) - Interviews
  - 7th Army in France and Germany, 1944-1945
  - Seventh Army Operations in Europe, 1944 August 15
  - Shinberger, John Baird
  - VI Corps
  - Southern France - Invasion of
    - 1st Airborne Task Force
    - 1st Airborne Task Force (Box 15)
  - 3rd Division
  - 3rd Regiment - Interviews
  - 34th Division
  - 36th Division
    - General
    - Miscellaneous
    - Questionnaires
  - U.S. military collaboration with Canada - World War II (Box 16)
  - Walton, Lieutenant Colonel George
- CLIPPINGS, 1940-1970 (Box 17)
- MISCELLANEOUS (Box 17)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, circa 1939-1945 (Envelope A)
  24 prints dealing with the First Special Service Force (US and Canadian troops) and its operations in Italy and Southern France during World War II.
- SOUND RECORDINGS (Tape cabinet)
  - The Champagne Campaign sound recordings (Reels 1-3)
    Access
    Use copy reference number: 72075_a_0004424
  - Rome Fell Today
    - Part 1 (Clark) (Reel 4)
    - Part 2 (Clark) (Reel 5)
    - Part 3 (Clark - Telephone) (Reel 6)
    - Part 4 (Eric Severeid) (Reel 7)
    - Part 5 (General Porter) (Reel 8)
    - Part 6 (Reel 9)
    - Part 7 (Reel 10)
    - Part 8 (Reel 11)
    - Part 9 (Reel 12)
    - Part 10 (Reel 13)
    - Part 11 (Reel 14)
    - Part 12 (Reel 15)
  - Rhone Valley (originals) (Reel 16)
    - Brigadier General Warner
    - Lieutenant General Quinn
    - Colonel Goinsboorgh
  - Interview with Colonel William Wyant, Washington, D.C., 1968 October 30 (Reel 17)
  - Colonel Alfred Howes (Reels 18-19)
  - Major General David G. Barr, Chief of Staff 6th Army Group (Reel 20)
  - Major General Eagles (Reels 21-22)
  - Major General Arthur A. White (Reels 23-25)
  - General Jacob Devers (Reels 26-28)